<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Fluidex</title>
  <subtitle></subtitle>
  <link href="https://www.fluidex.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://www.fluidex.io/"/>
  
    <updated>2021-03-03T08:00:00+08:00</updated>
  
  <id>https://www.fluidex.io</id>
  <author>
    <name>Author Name</name>
    <email>author@site.com</email>
  </author>
  
    
    <entry>
      <title>Fluidex: A ZK-Rollup layer2 DEX on Ethereum</title>
      <link href="https://www.fluidex.io/posts/2020-11-30-fluidex-a-zkrollup-layer2-dex/"/>
      <updated>2020-11-29T08:00:00+08:00</updated>
      <id>https://www.fluidex.io/posts/2020-11-30-fluidex-a-zkrollup-layer2-dex/</id>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
      <h1 id="what-is-fluidex"><a class="anchor-link" href="#what-is-fluidex"></a> What is FluiDex</h1>
<p>For those familiar with cutting-edge technology, FluiDex is a Layer 2 decentralized exchange on Ethereum. We will use PLONK-based zkrollup technology to achieve high-performance transactions, while being able to reduce the cost of each transaction to less than 1% of normal L1 transaction. We will be the first order book exchange on Ethereum to use PLONK based validity proof.</p>
<p>For the general public, FluiDex is a crypto asset exchange similar to Coinbase or Huobi. The advantage is that your assets are absolutely safe. You don’t need to trust the team of the exchange to be ethical or law-abiding. You only need to trust cryptography and code. The disadvantage is that it will be more difficult to use, for example, transaction fees will be higher in some cases.</p>
<h1 id="why-build-fluidex"><a class="anchor-link" href="#why-build-fluidex"></a> Why build FluiDex</h1>
<p>“Build a safe, professional and easy-to-use digital asset trading platform&quot; is our long-term vision.</p>
<p>In the scope of technology products that exist today, “security” means Ethereum, which requires almost no explanation. I will talk about how FluiDex understands “professional trading” in the below paragraph.</p>
<p>We roughly divide the traders in the market into two categories. One category is called “speculative retail investors”. The feature is that they don’t care about miners’ fees and handling fees, and don’t care about the slippage loss of market orders. They just want to be able to easily buy certain assets. Because they bet that this asset will increase several times, the other type, we call it “professional traders”, they care about miners’ fees and handling fees, they are skilled in using derivative hedging, they can arbitrage through different exchanges, and they are skilled in using limit/market/stoploss/FOK/IOC/AON order as a tool for different purposes, may use a program to do automatic trading.</p>
<p>On today’s Ethereum, exchanges such as Uniswap based on algorithm-based automated market making have gained high popularity. Except higher miner fees, such exchanges generally meet the needs of “speculative retail investors”. However, for this type of exchange, liquidity takers can only list market price orders. For liquidity maker, there will be profit due to rebates when the price is stable, and losses when the price fluctuates sharply. The above shortcomings can be tolerated for “speculative retail investors”, but they are unimaginable for “professional traders”. For every trader with a traditional financial background, if you tell them “there is no order book, you can’t place an order for rebates; you can only place a market order, and set a slippage threshold at most”, they will be shocked.</p>
<p>We expect that more and more real assets will circulate in a decentralized manner in the future, and more and more types of traders will participate in trading. Too simple swap exchanges will not be able to meet the needs of quite a few advanced traders. The traditional order book exchange will be a much easier solution.</p>
<p>So why hasn’t the order book decentralized exchange exploded in the past few years? On the one hand, it is the ecological environment. In the early years, there were not many assets carried on Ethereum. The USDT stablecoin, which is well-known to traders, did not circulate on Ethereum two years ago. On the other hand, technology. The early and simple implementation of order book exchanges will make the cost of miners’ fees for each commission and transaction comparable to swap exchanges. Expensive order and transaction costs constrain the explosion of order book exchanges. Today Thanks to the springing up of zero-knowledge proof technology in the past two years, we are finally able to provide a trading experience with zero-cost listing orders and 0.0001$-cost transaction.</p>
<p>In summary, the development of a decentralized economy has brought more and more traders and trading needs, and order book exchanges can better meet the needs of professional traders. In the past few years, the development of cryptography technology has made it possible for high-performance, low-cost and secure order book transactions. Therefore, it is time to build FluiDex now.</p>
<h1 id="similar-products-and-projects"><a class="anchor-link" href="#similar-products-and-projects"></a> Similar products and projects</h1>
<ol>
<li>Traditional centralized exchange. For quite a few, even more than half of the people, this type of exchange is good enough to use. However, for some people who have high requirements for fund security &amp; anonymity, the hidden danger of black swan always exists in centralized exchanges. Even for a big exchange like OKEx, it happened not long ago that the exchange was unable to withdraw the coin because the founder lost contact for more than a month.</li>
<li>Algorithmic automated market making exchange. Typical is Uniswap, which sets the price of buying and selling assets by always ensuring that the number of asset A * the number of asset B == the fixed value. In the previous paragraph, we believe that such exchanges are not enough for professional traders. But it must be acknowledged that the composability of such swap exchanges is an advantage that Layer2 DEX does not have, and Layer2 DEX is more difficult to become part of the “Defi building block”.</li>
<li>Order book exchange based on optimistic rollup technology. This type of exchange has high performance and is easy to develop, but it has two major disadvantages. The first is that withdrawing from such exchanges requires confirmation time of weeks, which is completely unacceptable for many traders. Second, the security of optimistic rollup is not as good as “as safe as L1” zk rollup.</li>
<li>Other products with similar technical decisions, such as diversifi and loopring. Yes, in a nutshell, FluiDex will compete head-to-head with them. That there are already one or two players in a potential big market, is not a reason why new players should not enter. It is not true that since OKEx is running well, Binance should not start a business. In addition, FluiDex and these projects will have some different decisions both in technology and product. For example, from a technical perspective, we will use PLONK as the protocol of zero-knowledge proof, which will bring faster product iteration, from a product perspective, we are likely to implement permissionless token listing.</li>
</ol>
<h1 id="decentralized-governance-%26-token"><a class="anchor-link" href="#decentralized-governance-%26-token"></a> Decentralized Governance &amp; Token</h1>
<p>I believe that our exchange is a traditional “centralized” exchange, the only difference is the self-custody of assets. There are many interpretations of “decentralization”, the decentralization of assets, the decentralization of control (“governance”), and even the decentralization of teams. Based on our vision, the decentralization of assets (ie, the self-custody of assets) is necessary for us. But, at least today, we believe that decentralization of governance is neither necessary nor sufficient for building a great product. Any team that does a product will investigate users and markets, but no team will decide the future of product only through user votes. Customers and shareholders are two kinds of people. You should not force or expect customers to become shareholders. For the FluiDex team, the customer is supreme, but there will be no so-called “decentralized” governance in the future. The decision-making power of the future of the product will always be in the hands of the management team, and users are expected to vote for our success or failure with their feet.</p>
<p>Based on our understanding of governance philosophy above, FluiDex will not issue “governance tokens” in the foreseeable future, but we are not opposed to issuing tokens with dividend rights for fundraising. For example, it is entirely possible for us to issue a token and guarantee to buy back this token with 10% of the monthly gross profit for the next 3 years.</p>
<h1 id="project-status-%26-schedule-%26-financing"><a class="anchor-link" href="#project-status-%26-schedule-%26-financing"></a> Project status &amp; schedule &amp; financing</h1>
<p>Fluidex project was launched at the end of 2020. It is expected that the MVP/demo will be completed in Q2 of 2021, and the mainnet launch will probably start in Q4 of 2021.</p>
<p>Update 2021.04.15:<br>
The project may soon launch a seed round of equity financing, and is looking for raising a total amount of around US$1 million, at a valuation of US$7-10 million, from all participating investors.</p>
<h1 id="contact"><a class="anchor-link" href="#contact"></a> Contact</h1>
<p>Telegram: <a href="https://t.me/fluid_dex">https://t.me/fluid_dex</a><br>
Medium: <a href="https://fluid-dex.medium.com/announcing-fluidex-building-the-first-plonk-layer2-dex-on-ethereum-e19136304a5d">https://fluid-dex.medium.com/announcing-fluidex-building-the-first-plonk-layer2-dex-on-ethereum-e19136304a5d</a><br>
Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/fluid_dex">https://twitter.com/fluid_dex</a><br>
Founder’s email: <a href="mailto:mycinbrin@gmail.com">mycinbrin@gmail.com</a></p>

    ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
  
    
    <entry>
      <title>Fluidex Recent Updates</title>
      <link href="https://www.fluidex.io/posts/2021-03-04-recent-updates/"/>
      <updated>2021-03-03T08:00:00+08:00</updated>
      <id>https://www.fluidex.io/posts/2021-03-04-recent-updates/</id>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
      <p>About us: The Fluidex team is developing the first zk-rollup layer2 order-book DEX with permissionless listings on Ethereum. For a more comprehensive introduction to the project, please see <a href="/posts/2020-11-30-fluidex-a-zkrollup-layer2-dex/">our previous article</a>.</p>
<p>In this post, We are happy to explain what we have achieved since the early 2021, at what time the project was launched.</p>
<h1 id="technical-progress"><a class="anchor-link" href="#technical-progress"></a> Technical progress</h1>
<h3>Plonkit</h3>
<p>As the saying goes, good tools are prerequisite to the success of a job.</p>
<p>Plonkit is a PLONK zero-knowledge proof toolkit developed by the Fluidex team. By using Plonkit, users can use an easier DSL (Circom) to implement their own zero-knowledge proof circuit code, without the need to learn the underlying cryptography library and how to write circuits in C or Rust (which is way more complicated).</p>
<p>The core of Plonkit is developed based on the bellman_ce cryptography library. The current functions include local setup (for development use only, in production better to use MPC ceremony), circuit proving and verification, solidity verification contract generation, etc.</p>
<p>Plonkit has received a lot of attention from developers since being open sourced, and it is now the project with the most stars on github by the team.</p>
<p>We are implementing server mode so that plonkit can serve for continuously-running proving service. In the future, we will further implement the cluster proving server feature. In a longer term, we may add custom gates to further improve the performance of the system. In addition, we will continue to improve DSL specifically for PLONK and its variants.</p>
<p>For more, please visit github: <a href="https://github.com/Fluidex/plonkit">https://github.com/Fluidex/plonkit</a></p>
<h3>Exchange</h3>
<p>In the past a few months, the Fluidex team has finished the first version of the exchange matching engine backend and web frontend. The backend of the matching engine has been open sourced, using Rust language to implement in-memory order matching, which can achieve thousands of TPS. This will ensure the fluency and stability of our trading system in the foreseeable future.  We are still improving this system continuously. (It hasn’t been tempered by real business, so it is only recommended to be used only for learning and communication at present rather than production).</p>
<p>Currently, the back end of the exchange has been open sourced, and the front end has not yet been open sourced.<br>
For more details, please visit github: <a href="https://github.com/Fluidex/dingir-exchange">https://github.com/Fluidex/dingir-exchange</a></p>
<h3>Zero-knowledge proof circuit and smart contract</h3>
<p>We have delivered <a href="https://github.com/Fluidex/rescue-hash-js">the first implementation of Javascript Rescue Hash</a>, and also developed <a href="https://github.com/Fluidex/circuits/blob/master/src/lib/rescue.circom">the first circom implementation of Rescue Hash circuit</a>. Based on the Echarts sunburst chart, we have developed <a href="https://github.com/Fluidex/circuits/blob/master/tools/benchmark/profile_circuit.js">a tool for profiling circuits visually</a>. So users can analyze their own circuit code more conveniently, finding which parts of the circuits lead to the major computation overhead, so they can make further optimization accordingly.</p>
<p>We have prototyped the most basic circuit code for deposit, withdrawal &amp; transfer &amp; trading. There are still many functions and performance details that need to be further improved, so we will not introduce it for the time being. Of course, all the code is at a very early stage, without any audit, it is not recommended for production use.</p>
<p>All the above results have been open sourced in our code base. For more details, please visit github: <a href="https://github.com/Fluidex/circuits">https://github.com/Fluidex/circuits</a></p>
<h3>Awesome Plonk</h3>
<p>This is a collection of high-quality materials about PLONK. It covers various learning materials such as papers, implementations, demos, forums, blog posts, videos, etc.</p>
<p>For more details, please visit github: <a href="https://github.com/Fluidex/awesome-plonk">https://github.com/Fluidex/awesome-plonk</a></p>
<h1 id="community-status"><a class="anchor-link" href="#community-status"></a> Community Status</h1>
<p>Currently we only maintain the English technical community on Telegram. More than 100 developers who are interested in our project have joined in the past two months. In the future, we will continue to update our technological progress there.</p>
<h1 id="financing-status"><a class="anchor-link" href="#financing-status"></a> Financing status</h1>
<p>In the past few months, Fluidex has raised a total of more than US$500,000 from several private investors. We would like to thank these seniors in the industry for their financial and other support.</p>
<p>The money is sufficient for our current development. We are not seeking further financing for the time being.</p>
<h1 id="technical-contribution-to-other-projects"><a class="anchor-link" href="#technical-contribution-to-other-projects"></a> Technical contribution to other projects</h1>
<p>We found a <a href="https://github.com/matter-labs/zksync/pull/284">bug when the number of inputs is greater than 1</a>, in the open sourced PLONK solidity verification contract code of Matters Lab, and submitted an upstream pull request. (The zksync online system does not trigger this code path, and the correctness and safety are not affected by this bug.)</p>
<p>Fluidex is participating into the phase 2 trusted setup ceremony of the Hermez project, hoping to contribute to the wider Layer2 community through its own strength. (Explanation: What is the “phase 2 trusted setup ceremony”? The zk-rollup projects that use Groth16 protocol need to ensure the security of some cryptographic parameters by using multi-party computations. The “phase 2 trusted setup ceremony” is one of such multi-party computations. As long as at least one of the participants is honest, the entropy and hence randomness can be guaranteed. Provers then cannot forge a proof.)</p>

    ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
  
</feed>